Trudy Griffin-Pierce and Keith Pierce Papers 1938-2009 (bulk 1980-2008)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Trudy Griffin-Pierce and Keith Pierce Papers
1938-2009
(bulk 1980-2008)
MS 499
Griffin-Pierce, Trudy, 1949-2009;; Pierce, Kieth
This collection is comprised of the papers of anthropologist Trudy Griffin-Pierce and solar astronomer Keith Pierce. The bulk of the material relates to Trudy Griffin-Pierce’s career as an anthropologist at the University of Arizona as well as her personal journals. Items include writings, correspondence, academic material as well as some personal material. Also included are some papers of Keith Pierce, primarily copies of his autobiography.
17 linear ft.
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://www.library.arizona.edu/speccoll
Restrictions
Personal journal volumes 50-104 located in Series V Boxes 9-16 are restricted until 2029.
Biographical Note
Trudy Griffin-Pierce was born December 27, 1949 in South Carolina to Ben and Trudy Griffin. Due to Ben Griffin’s career as an Air Force officer, she spent her childhood travelling including living in Florida, Hawaii, England and California. When she was 16 her mother died suddenly of an aneurysm which became a pivotal experience in her life. She earned her Bachelor of Arts degree from Florida State University in printmaking and fine arts. While she was a student there she wrote to the Navajo Tribal Chairman asking if she could join a traditional Navajo family as a daughter. After spending time in Many Farms, Arizona with her Navajo family who she maintained a relationship with for the rest of her life, she returned to Florida to finish her degree. She returned to Arizona and enrolled at the University of Arizona as a graduate student in fine arts but switched to anthropology and earned a Master of Arts in museum studies in 1970. She worked as a curator at the Indian Pueblo Culture Center as well as at the Kitt Peak National Observatory museum. There she met Keith Pierce who she married in 1979. She returned to the University of Arizona and earned a doctorate in anthropology in 1987.
Dr. Griffin-Pierce specialized in medical anthropology and native cultures with projects. She was an adjunct lecturer at the University from 1988 to 2003, assistant professor of anthropology from 2003 to 2008 and gained tenure as an associate professor in 2008. She authored six books including Earth is my Mother, Sky is my Father: Space, Time and Astronomy in Navajo Sandpainting (1992), Native Americans: Enduring Culture and Traditions (1996), The Encyclopedia of Native America (1995), Native Peoples of the Southwest (2000) which won the Alice Logan Writing Award in 2000, Chiricahua Apache Enduring Power: Naiche’s Puberty Ceremony Paintings (2007) which won the Southern Anthropological Society’s James Mooney Award in 2008 and The Colombia Guide to American Indians of the Southwest (2010). Dr. Griffin-Pierce was also an artist and did much of the art work for her books herself. She died January 6, 2009.
Austin Keith Pierce was born on October 2, 1918 in Tacoma, Washington to Tracy and Lucy Pierce. He was introduced early to telescopes as his father, a mathematics professor at the University of Nebraska, Lincoln, who built telescopes at home. He attended the University of Nebraska, Lincoln, from 1936 to 1938 but eventually moved to Berkeley where he graduated from the University of California, Berkeley with a Bachelor of Science degree in astronomy. He married Mildred Buell in 1941 and had three children, Barbara, John and Ross. During World War II he worked on uranium isotope separation at the E.O. Lawrence Radiation Laboratory calutron in Berkeley as well as in Oak Ridge, Tennessee. He returned to Berkeley in 1945 and earned his doctorate in Astronomy in 1948 under Dr. C.D. Shane.
After graduation he was recruited by Leo Goldberg from the University of Michigan, Ann Arbor to be a research assistant, he then moved to the McMath-Hulbert Observatory near Pontiac, Michigan. Dr. McMath found funding to develop the world’s largest solar telescope at Kitt Peak which Dr. Pierce helped site and design. He was appointed Associate Director in charge of the Solar Division which he held for 16 years. Dr. Pierce greatly contributed to work on the solar spectrum, especially the ultraviolet and infrared frontiers and was also a pioneer in the use of infrared and photoelectric detectors to make accurate measurements. At the 30th anniversary of the dedication of the McMath Solar Telescope in 1992 it was renamed the McMath-Pierce Solar Telescope in honor of his contribution to the development of the facility. He died on March 11, 2005.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into 7 series.
Series I: Personal Files, 1961-2008
Series II: Correspondence, 1938-2007
Series III: Writings, 1985-2009
Subseries 1: Manuscripts, 1985-2007
Subseries 2: Articles, 1988-1992
Subseries 3: Book Reviews, 1988-2009
Series IV: Academic Files, 1976-2008
Series V: Journals, 1967-2008
Series VI: Keith Pierce Files, 1964-1982
Series VII: Oversize, 1992-2008
Scope and Content Note
Papers, 1938-2009 (1980-2008). This collection consists primarily of the papers of Trudy Griffin-Pierce relating to her professional career as an anthropologist as well as her journals spanning 40 years. The bulk of the material consists of her writings, academic material including material from her graduate education and teaching career as well as correspondence, personal material and her personal journals. Also included is material from solar astronomer Keith Pierce primarily drafts of his autobiography as well as astronomy notes.
Access Terms
Griffin-Pierce, Trudy, 1949-2009
Pierce, A. Keith.
Astronomy.
Indians of North America -- Southwest, New.
Kitt Peak National Observatory.
Navajo Indians.
University of Arizona.
Autobiography.
Journals.
Manuscripts.
Container List
- Series I: Personal Files, 1961-2008
  This series contains personal material associated with Trudy Griffin-Pierce. It includes calendars, personal notebooks and ledgers, receipts and correspondence related to her artwork. This series is arranged alphabetically.
  - Artist work, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Artist work, 1979-2006 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Calendars, 1971-1989 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Calendars, 1990-1999 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Calendars, 2000-2009 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Notes, 1978-2008, undated (Box 1, Folder 7-11)
  - Professional record, 1976, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - School assignments, 1961-1965 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Thankfulness notebooks, 1997-2002 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Thankfulness notebooks, 2005-2008 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Series II: Correspondence, 1938-2007
  This series contains personal and professional correspondence including some correspondence between Trudy Griffin-Pierce’s parents, Ben and Trudy. This series is arranged alphabetically by last name with items in folders arranged chronologically.
  - A-P, 1982-2007 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Pierce, Ben and Trudy, 1944-1970 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Kux, Claudia, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - NHNZ, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Pierce, Keith, 1938-1998, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Washburn, Dorothy, 1998-1999 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Series III: Writings, 1985-2009
  This series contains published and unpublished writings. It is divided into 3 subseries, manuscripts, articles, and book reviews. The material is arranged alphabetically by title.
  - Manuscripts, 1985-2007
    This sub-series contains drafts of manuscripts.
    - The Artist as Anthropologist: Achieving a Deeper Understanding of the Creative Process in the Constitution of Navajo Sacred Sandpaintings, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Ben and Trudy, 1995-2001 (Box 2, Folder 7-14)
    - Beyond the Scalpel and the Silver Bear: Bridging the Chasm between Biomedical Research and “Biocolonialism”, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Black God: God of Fire, God of Starlight, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Camel Dreaming, ca. 1992 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Camels in the Outback, ca. 1992 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Challenges to Developing Neuropsychological Instruments for Assessing Alzheimer’s Disease in American Indians and Alaska Natives, 2006-2007 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Chiricahua Apache enduring Power: Naiche’s Puberty Ceremony Paintings, 1999-2007 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Cognition and Social Memory: The Role of Cultural Models in the Formation of Social Memory in Chiricahua Apache Prisoner of War Paintings, 2005-2006 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
    - Colombia Guide to American Indians of the Southwest, 2004-2008 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Consensus and Variation in Depiction and Interpretation of Constellations in Navajo Sandpaintings, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - The Continuous Renewal of Sacred Relations: Navajo Religion, 1996; 2000 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Creating a Culturally Appropriate Smoking Cessation Program with American Indians and Alaska Natives, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Earth is my Mother, Sky is my Father: Space, Time, and Astronomy in Navajo Sandpainting, 1985-1995 (Box 3, Folder 7-12)
    - The Encyclopedia of Native America, 1992-1996 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Hopi and Zuni Prayer Sticks: Magic, Symbolic Texts, Gifts, or Persons?, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - How Navajo Sandpaintings Accomplish the Work of Healing, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Learning to see what is Really There: Reconstructing Cultural Models with Navajo Chanters, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Microsoft Encarta articles, 2001-2002 (Box 3, Folder 17-18)
    - Mirindi Mick, the Magical Camel, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Native Peoples of the Southwest, 1999-2000 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Navajo Ceremonial Sandpainting: Sacred, Living Entities, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - The Navajo Nation and the Unites States Today, 2006-2007 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Navajo Sandpaintings of the Heavens, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Navajo Stars: Variation in one domain of Cultural Knowledge, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - North America essay, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Photographs as Foci for Informant Interviews in Two Cultures, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Recording and Using Sacred Knowledge: When an Anthropologist and Navajo People work together, 2007 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - The Sacred Sky: Native American Star Knowledge, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Time, Self and Society, 2000-2004 (Box 4, Folder 9-10)
    - Treasure Mapping, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Subseries: Articles, 1988-1992
    This series contains published copes of articles.
    - The American Anthropological Association on Session “Visions of the Sky: Studies in North American Ethnoastronomy”, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Cosmological Order as a Model for Navajo Philosophy, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - The Hooghan and the Stars, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Subseries: Book Reviews, 1988-2009
    This series contains published copies of book reviews,
    - Desert Indian Women: Stories and Dreams, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Living Life’s Circle: Mescalero Apache Cosmovision, 1993-1998 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - The Multicultural Southwest: A Reader, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Navajo Medicine Bundles or Jish, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Surviving the Conquest: A History of the Yavapai Peoples, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Voice in Clay: Pueblo Pottery from the Edna M. Kelly Collection, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Weaving Women’s Lives: Three Generations in a Navajo Family, 2009 (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Series IV: Academic Files, 1976-2008
  This series contains material related to Trudy Griffin-Pierce's academic career including graduate school notes, teaching material such as lecture notes as well as material from different projects and conferences.
  - Alzheimer’s Disease research, 2007-2008 (Box 4, Folder 22-24)
  - Anthropology 206, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Anthropology 206, 1998, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Anthropology 206 Honors, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 27-28)
  - Anthropology 413, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Anthropology 476, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Anthropology 478, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Anthropology 483, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Anthropology 600, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Anthropology/History 148, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Appointments, 1981-2008 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Arizona Lecture Series, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Art History 112, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Art History 233, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Clara Lee Tanner talk, 1991-1992 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Colloquium in honor of Susan Phillips, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Colorado River Indian Tribes lecture, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Dancing of the Dreaming symposium, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Death and Dying conference session abstracts, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Departmental correspondence, 2006-2008 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Dissertation defense notes, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Dissertation notebooks, 1985-1986 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Encouraging Healthy Lifestyles of Diabetic Patients through Native Practitioners, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Film requests, 1996-2003 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Indian Pueblo Culture Center, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - INDV 102, 2000-2002 (Box 5, Folder 19-20)
  - INDV 102, 2008 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Junior Faculty Professional Development leave, 2003-2007 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - ‘Learning to see what is Really There’ Making Neuropsychological Instruments Culturally Important, 2006 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Miscellaneous class essays, 1981-1982 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Miscellaneous class notes, 2003, 2008, undated (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Mountain Lions and other animals, 1989-1992 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Native American art lecture notes, undated (Box 5, Folder 27-28)
  - Navajo Code Talker documentary, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Navajo medical lectures, 1993-1994 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Navajo papers, 1981-1983 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - The Navajo Philosophy of Healing, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Navajo Philosophy of life program, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Navajo Sandpaintings of the Heavens, 1987-1989 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Notes, 1985-2008, undated (Box 6, Folder 4-6)
  - Preliminaries notebook, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Sandpaintings, undated (Box 6, Folder 8-15)
  - Sandpaintings, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Statement of Accomplishment and Objectives on Research, Teaching, and Service/Outreach, 2007-2008 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Student evaluations, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Tonga notebook, 1985, 1989 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Tonga research, 1984-1989 (Box 7, Folder 5-6)
  - Undergraduate class notes, undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Visual Prayers: The Paintings and Drawings of Native American Prisoners of War slides, undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Walking in Beauty: The Dennys, a Family of Navajo Chanters, 2007 (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Series V: Keith Pierce Files, 1964-1982
  This series contains the material of Keith Pierce with drafts of his autobiography making up the majority of the material. Also included are his notes on astronomy and some memos from the Kitt Peak National Observatory.
  - Biographical data, undated (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - The Illustrated Autobiography of Austin Keith Pierce, undated (Box 7, Folder 11-14)
  - Kitt Peak National Observatory, 1964-1966 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous, 1970, 1982, undated (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Notes, undated (Box 7, Folder 17-18)
- Series VI: Journals, 1967-2008
  This series contains the personal journals of Trudy Griffin-Pierce. They detail her life from her time on the Navajo Reservation as an adopted daughter until her death in 2009. She includes all aspects of her life, personally and professionally. Volumes 1-2 are not included in this collection. Volumes 50-104 are restricted until 2029.
  - Volume 3, 1967-1968 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Volume 4, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Volume 5, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Volume 6, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Volume 7, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Volume 8, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Volume 9, 1968-1969 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Volume 10, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Volume 11, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Volume 12, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Volume 13, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Volume 14, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Volume 15, 1969-1970 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Volume 16, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Volume 17, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Volume 18, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Volume 19, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Volume 20, 1970-1971 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Volume 21, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Volume 22, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Volume 23, 1971-1972 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Volume 24, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Volume 25, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Volume 26, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Volume 27, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Volume 28, 1972-1973 (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Volume 28a, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Volume 29, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Volume 30, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - Volume 31, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - Volume 32, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 31)
  - Volume 33, 1973-1974 (Box 8, Folder 32)
  - Volume 34, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 33)
  - Volume 35, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 34)
  - Volume 36, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 35)
  - Volume 37, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 36)
  - Volume 38, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 37)
  - Volume 39, 1974-1975 (Box 8, Folder 38)
  - Volume 40, 1975 (Box 8, Folder 39)
  - Volume 41, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Volume 42, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Volume 43, 1975-1976 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Volume 44, 1976 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Volume 45, 1976 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Volume 46, 1976 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Volume 47, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Volume 48, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Volume 49, 1977-1978 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Volume 50, 1978-1979 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Volume 51, 1979-1980 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Volume 52, 1980 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Volume 53, 1980 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Volume 54, 1981 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Volume 55, 1981 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Volume 56, undated (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Volume 57, 1982-1983 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Volume 58, 1983 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Volume 59, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Volume 60, 1984-1985 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Volume 61, 1985-1986 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Volume 62, 1986-1987 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Volume 63, 1987-1988 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Volume 64, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Volume 65, 1988-1989 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Volume 66, 1989-1990 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Volume 67, 1990 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Volume 68, 1990-1991 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Volume 69, 1991 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Volume 70, 1991 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Volume 71, 1991 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Volume 72, 1991-1992 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Volume 73, 1992 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Volume 74, 1992 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Volume 75, 1992-1993 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Volume 76, 1993 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Volume 77, 1993 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Volume 78, 1993-1994 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Volume 79, 1994 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Volume 80, 1994 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Volume 81, 1995 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Volume 82, 1995-1996 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Volume 83, 1996 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Volume 84, 1996-1997 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Volume 85, 1997 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Volume 86, 1997-1998 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Volume 87, 1998-1999 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Volume 88, 1999-2000 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Volume 89, 2000-2001 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Volume 90a, 2001 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Volume 90, 2001 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Volume 91, 2001-2002 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Volume 92, 2002 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Volume 93, 2003 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Volume 94, 2003-2004 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Volume 95, 2004-2005 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Volume 96, 2005 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Volume 97, 2005 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Volume 98, 2005-2006 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Volume 99, 2006 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Volume 100, 2007 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Volume 101, 2007-2008 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Volume 102, 2008 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Volume 103, 2008 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Volume 104, 2008 (Box 16, Folder 4)
- Series VII: Oversize, 1994-2008
  This series contains oversize calendars from the personal series.
  - Calendars, 1994-2008 (Box 17, Folder 1)